<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- 
For use when a committee document points at the OASIS web site for publishing:
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" 
href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/templates/DocBook/spec-0.8/stylesheets/oasis-specification-html.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" 

For use when a committee document points to an embedded installation of DocBook
(note the instructions for embedding DocBook requires pruning some directories
and adjusting the stylesheet and DocBook directories in these declarations):
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" 
      href="../htmlruntime/spec-0.8/stylesheets/oasis-note-html-offline.xsl"?>
<?oasis-spec-base-uri ../htmlruntime/spec-0.8/?>
<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
        "../htmlruntime/spec-0.8/docbook/docbookx.dtd" 

For use when a committee document is published in a local environment only
(note the instructions for local publishing require adjusting the stylesheet
 and DocBook directories in these declarations):
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" 
href="file:///Users/admin/z/oasis/spec-0.8/stylesheets/oasis-specification-html-offline.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
         "file:///Users/admin/z/oasis/spec-0.8/docbook/docbookx.dtd" 
-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" 
      href="../htmlruntime/spec-0.8/stylesheets/oasis-note-html-offline.xsl"?>
<?oasis-spec-base-uri ../htmlruntime/spec-0.8/?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../htmlruntime/spec-0.8/docbook/docbookx.dtd" [
<!--the document properties-->
<!ENTITY dir "VEL">
<!ENTITY name "&dir;-v&version;">
<!ENTITY pstage "xxxx">
<!ENTITY version "1.0">
<!ENTITY stage "csprd01">
<!ENTITY title "Variability Exchange Language Version &version;">
<!ENTITY standard "Committee Specification Draft 01 / Public Review Draft 01">
<!ENTITY this-loc "https://docs.oasis-open.org/vel/&dir;/v&version;/&stage;">
<!ENTITY previous-loc "https://docs.oasis-open.org/vel/&dir;/v&version;/&pstage;">
<!ENTITY latest-loc "https://docs.oasis-open.org/vel/&dir;/v&version;">
<!ENTITY pubdate "13 November 2020">
<!ENTITY % MATHML.prefixed "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MATHML.prefix "mml">
<!ENTITY % equation.content "(alt?, (graphic+|mediaobject+|mml:math))">
<!ENTITY % inlineequation.content "(alt?, (inlinegraphic+|inlinemediaobject+|mml:math))">
<!ENTITY % mathml PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD MathML 2.0//EN" "http://www.w3.org/Math/DTD/mathml2/mathml2.dtd">
]>
<article status="Committee Specification Draft 01 / Public Review Draft 01">
  <articleinfo>
    <productname>&name;</productname>

    <productnumber>&stage;</productnumber>

    <releaseinfo role="track">Standards Track</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo
    role="OASIS-specification-this-authoritative">&this-loc;/&name;-&stage;.html</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo
    role="OASIS-specification-this">&this-loc;/&name;-&stage;.pdf</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo
    role="OASIS-specification-this">&this-loc;/&name;-&stage;.xml</releaseinfo>

    <!--
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-previous-authoritative">&previous-loc;/&name;-&pstage;.html</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-previous">&previous-loc;/&name;-&pstage;.pdf</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-previous">&previous-loc;/&name;-&pstage;.xml</releaseinfo>
-->

    <releaseinfo
    role="OASIS-specification-latest-authoritative">&latest-loc;/&name;.html</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo
    role="OASIS-specification-latest">&latest-loc;/&name;.pdf</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo
    role="OASIS-specification-latest">&latest-loc;/&name;.xml</releaseinfo>

    <releaseinfo role="committee"><ulink conformance="skip"
    url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/vel">OASIS Variability Exchange
    Language (VEL) TC</ulink></releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <editor>
        <firstname>Michael</firstname>

        <surname>Schulze</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink conformance="skip"
          url="http://www.pure-systems.com/">pure-systems
          GmbH</ulink></orgname>
        </affiliation>

        <email>michael.schulze@pure-systems.com</email>
      </editor>

      <editor>
        <firstname>Uwe</firstname>

        <surname>Ryssel</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink conformance="skip"
          url="http://www.pure-systems.com/">pure-systems
          GmbH</ulink></orgname>
        </affiliation>

        <email>uwe.ryssel@pure-systems.com</email>
      </editor>

      <!-- Chairs -->

      <othercredit>
        <firstname>Michael</firstname>

        <surname>Schulze</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink conformance="skip"
          url="http://www.pure-systems.com/">pure-systems
          GmbH</ulink></orgname>
        </affiliation>

        <email>michael.schulze@pure-systems.com</email>
      </othercredit>

      <othercredit>
        <firstname>Uwe</firstname>

        <surname>Ryssel</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname><ulink conformance="skip"
          url="http://www.pure-systems.com/">pure-systems
          GmbH</ulink></orgname>
        </affiliation>

        <email>uwe.ryssel@pure-systems.com</email>
      </othercredit>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>&pubdate;</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2020</year>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice role="additional">
      <title>Additional artifacts</title>

      <para>This prose specification is one component of a Work Product which
      also includes:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>{XML schemas}</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>{Other parts}</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </legalnotice>

    <legalnotice role="related">
      <title>Related work</title>

      <para>This specification replaces or supersedes:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>{specification replaced by this standard}</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>{specification replaced by this standard}</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This specification is related to:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>{related specifications}</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>{related specifications}</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </legalnotice>

    <legalnotice role="namespaces">
      <title>Declared XML namespaces</title>

      <para><ulink
      url="https://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/vel/xxxx">https://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/vel/xxxx</ulink></para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>The Variability Exchange Language (VEL) enables the exchange of
      variability information among tools for variant management tools and
      systems development tools. VEL eliminates the cost of building
      customized interfaces by defining a standard way for information to be
      exchanged among corresponding tools. Using VEL, a variant management
      tool is able to read the variability from a development tool and pass
      configurations of selected system features to a development tool.</para>

      <para>By defining a common variability data interface that can be
      implemented by both the development tools and the variant management
      tools, VEL enables a continuous development process for variable systems
      and more flexible use of tools.</para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice role="status">
      <title>Status</title>

      <para>This document was last revised or approved by the OASIS
      Variability Exchange Language (VEL) TC on the above date. The level of
      approval is also listed above. Check the &ldquo;Latest stage&rdquor;
      location noted above for possible later revisions of this document. Any
      other numbered Versions and other technical work produced by the
      Technical Committee (TC) are listed at <ulink
      url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=vel#technical">https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=vel#technical</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Technical Committee members should send comments on this
      specification to the TC&rsquor;s email list. Others should send comments
      to the TC by using the &ldquo;<ulink conformance="skip"
      url="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/comments/index.php?wg_abbrev=vel">Send
      A Comment</ulink>&rdquor; button on the TC&rsquor;s web page at <ulink
      url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/vel/">https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/vel/</ulink>.</para>

      <para>This specification is provided under the <ulink conformance="skip"
      url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr/#Non-Assertion-Mode">Non-Assertion
      </ulink> Mode of the OASIS IPR Policy, the mode chosen when the
      Technical Committee was established. For information on whether any
      patents have been disclosed that may be essential to implementing this
      specification, and any offers of patent licensing terms, please refer to
      the Intellectual Property Rights section of the TC&rsquor;s web page
      (<ulink
      url="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/vel/ipr.php">https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/vel/ipr.php</ulink>).</para>

      <para>Note that any machine-readable content (<ulink
      url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/tc-process#wpComponentsCompLang">Computer
      Language Definitions</ulink>) declared Normative for this Work Product
      is provided in separate plain text files. In the event of a discrepancy
      between any such plain text file and display content in the Work
      Product&rsquor;s prose narrative document(s), the content in the
      separate plain text file prevails.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <legalnotice role="citation">
      <title>Citation format</title>

      <para>When referencing this specification the following citation format
      should be used:</para>

      <bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed conformance="skip"><abbrev>&name;</abbrev>
        <citetitle>&title;. </citetitle> <bibliomisc>Edited by Michael Schulze
        and Uwe Ryssel. </bibliomisc> <date>&pubdate;. </date>
        <releaseinfo>OASIS &standard;. </releaseinfo> <bibliomisc><ulink
        url="https://docs.oasis-open.org/vel/VEL/v1.0/csprd01/VEL-v1.0-csprd01.html">&this-loc;/&name;-&stage;.html</ulink>.
        Latest version: <ulink
        url="https://docs.oasis-open.org/vel/VEL/v1.0/VEL-v1.0.html">&latest-loc;/&name;.html</ulink>.</bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist>
    </legalnotice>

    <legalnotice role="notices">
      <title>Notices</title>

      <para>Copyright © OASIS Open 2019. All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>All capitalized terms in the following text have the meanings
      assigned to them in the OASIS Intellectual Property Rights Policy (the
      &ldquo;OASIS IPR Policy&rdquor;). The full <ulink conformance="skip"
      url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/ipr">Policy</ulink>
      may be found at the OASIS website.</para>

      <para>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished
      to others, and derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it
      or assist in its implementation may be prepared, copied, published, and
      distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of any kind,
      provided that the above copyright notice and this section are included
      on all such copies and derivative works. However, this document itself
      may not be modified in any way, including by removing the copyright
      notice or references to OASIS, except as needed for the purpose of
      developing any document or deliverable produced by an OASIS Technical
      Committee (in which case the rules applicable to copyrights, as set
      forth in the OASIS IPR Policy, must be followed) or as required to
      translate it into languages other than English.</para>

      <para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not
      be revoked by OASIS or its successors or assigns.</para>

      <para>This document and the information contained herein is provided on
      an &ldquo;AS IS&rdquor; basis and OASIS DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES,
      EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE
      USE OF THE INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY OWNERSHIP RIGHTS AND
      ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
      PURPOSE.</para>

      <para>OASIS requests that any OASIS Party or any other party that
      believes it has patent claims that would necessarily be infringed by
      implementations of this OASIS Committee Specification or OASIS Standard
      notify OASIS TC Administrator and provide an indication of its
      willingness to grant patent licenses to such patent claims in a manner
      consistent with the IPR Mode of the OASIS Technical Committee that
      produced this specification.</para>

      <para>OASIS invites any party to contact the OASIS TC Administrator if
      it is aware of a claim of ownership of any patent claims that would
      necessarily be infringed by implementations of this specification by a
      patent holder that is not willing to provide a license to such patent
      claims in a manner consistent with the IPR Mode of the OASIS Technical
      Committee that produced this specification. OASIS may include such
      claims on its website, but disclaims any obligation to do so.</para>

      <para>OASIS takes no position regarding the validity or scope of any
      intellectual property or other rights that might be claimed to pertain
      to the implementation or use of the technology described in this
      document or the extent to which any license under such rights might or
      might not be available; neither does it represent that it has made any
      effort to identify any such rights. Information on OASIS&rsquor;
      procedures with respect to rights in any document or deliverable
      produced by an OASIS Technical Committee can be found on the OASIS
      website. Copies of claims of rights made available for publication and
      any assurances of licenses to be made available, or the result of an
      attempt made to obtain a general license or permission for the use of
      such proprietary rights by implementers or users of this OASIS Committee
      Specification or OASIS Standard, can be obtained from the OASIS TC
      Administrator. OASIS makes no representation that any information or
      list of intellectual property rights will at any time be complete, or
      that any claims in such list are, in fact, Essential Claims.</para>

      <para>The name &ldquo;OASIS&rdquor; is a trademark of <ulink
      conformance="skip" url="https://www.oasis-open.org">OASIS</ulink>, the
      owner and developer of this specification, and should be used only to
      refer to the organization and its official outputs. OASIS welcomes
      reference to, and implementation and use of, specifications, while
      reserving the right to enforce its marks against misleading uses. Please
      see <ulink
      url="https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark">https://www.oasis-open.org/policies-guidelines/trademark</ulink>
      for guidance.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="S-INTRODUCTION">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section id="S-OVERVIEW">
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>VEL is an interoperability standard that enables the exchange of
      variability information among variant management tools and systems
      development tools. The essential tasks of a variants management tool are
      to represent and analyze the variability of a system abstractly and to
      define system configurations by selecting the desired system features. A
      system development tool captures information of a specific kind, such as
      requirements, architecture, component design, or tests. In order to
      support the development of variable systems a development tool either
      has to offer the capability to express and deal with variability
      directly, or an adaptor must be provided that adds this capability to
      the development tool.</para>

      <para>To interconnect variants management with systems development the
      information exchange among the corresponding tools must be established.
      A variants management tool must be able to read or extract the
      variability from a development tool and to pass a configuration, i.e. a
      set of selected system features, to the development tool. Up to now the
      interfaces that support this information exchange are built for each
      development tool anew. With VEL&lt;emphasis&gt;,&lt;/emphasis&gt; a
      common interface is defined that can be implemented by both the
      development tools and the variants management tool, thus VEL eliminates
      the cost of building customized interfaces by defining a standard way
      for information to be exchanged between tools.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Variants Management, System Variability, and Variation
        Points</title>

        <para>Variants management is an activity that accompanies the whole
        system development process and, therefore, is orthogonal to the other
        development tasks. Like safety, security, and other system properties,
        variability cannot be built into a system at the end of the process.
        Rather, the desired variability has to be determined, analyzed,
        designed, implemented and tested continuously, starting at the very
        beginning of the process through to the final delivery of the system
        or the system variant respectively. That means that within each
        development stage &ndash; requirements analysis, design,
        implementation, test, documentation, etc. &ndash; variability is an
        aspect that has to be considered.</para>

        <para>We consider as variable system a system that can be tailored by
        the system producer according to individual clients&rsquor; needs. All
        variants of a variable system are developed within one development
        process. In addition to the standard development tasks the process
        must also provide the means to tailor the system, i.e. to derive the
        client specific variant of the system. This may happen at different
        stages, also known as (variance) binding times.</para>

        <para>Variability is embodied in variation points. Consider as example
        a requirements document. A requirement toward a variable system may be
        <emphasis>optional</emphasis>. In this case, two system variants can
        be formed by either selecting or deselecting the requirement. A set of
        requirements may be <emphasis>alternatives</emphasis>, then each
        selection of one of these requirements forms one system variant.
        Finally, a requirement may contain a <emphasis>parameter</emphasis>,
        and then each value that can be selected for this parameter yields a
        system variant.</para>

        <para>The same definition of variation points holds for all other
        artifacts that are created in the development process &ndash; be it
        analysis or design models such as the views defined in the meta model,
        test specifications, code, documentation, or whatever. In each
        artifact there may be optional elements, alternative elements, and
        parameterized elements.</para>

        <para>We do not specify here how these variation points are
        represented in the artifacts. Some artifact formats support the
        definition of variation points, in other cases appropriate means have
        to be added. This obviously also has an impact on the tools that are
        used to create and manage the artifacts. In some cases they are
        capable to express variation points. In other cases adaptors have to
        be built in order to incorporate variation points.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Variability View and Variants Management Tools</title>

        <para>It is an accepted best practice to define an explicit abstract
        variability view on a system under development to support variants
        management continuously throughout the process. This abstraction
        contains the bare information on the variability of the system. That
        means that it describes which variants exist, but does not describe
        how the variability is realized. The variability information is
        derived from an analysis of the commonalities, differences, and
        dependencies of the system&rsquor;s variants and is often represented
        as a feature model.</para>

        <para>A variants management tool supports the creation of an artifact
        &ndash; a variability model &ndash; that represents the abstract
        variability information. Moreover, it offers operations to select or
        deselect system features and via this feature configuration to specify
        the system&rsquor;s variants.</para>

        <para>The information of the variability view has to be connected with
        the system development artifacts in order to define how the feature
        selection (system configuration) determines the resolution of the
        variation points within these artifacts, i.e. the selection of a
        variation for each variation point. As soon as these connections are
        established a feature configuration can be carried over to a
        configuration of the variation points of the concerned artifact. The
        technical realization of this connection is addressed by the
        <emphasis>Variability Exchange Language</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>At present there is no standard that would define how variation
        points are expressed in different artifacts. That means that a tool
        supplier who builds a variants management tool has to implement an
        individual interface to each other tool that is used in a development
        process to create the corresponding artifacts. The purpose of the
        <emphasis>Variability Exchange Language</emphasis> is to support the
        standardization of these interfaces by a common exchange format that
        defines which information is exchanged between a variants management
        tool and a tool that is used to manage a specific kind of artifacts in
        a development process. As mentioned above, such a tool may either be a
        tool that already supports the definition of variation points for the
        concerned artifact type, or it may be an adaptor that adds this
        capability to a base tool.</para>

        <para>The <emphasis>Variability Exchange Language</emphasis> defines a
        requirement on tools or tool adaptors that intend to support variants
        management. Such a tool has to be able to extract the data that is
        defined in the <emphasis>Variability Exchange Language</emphasis> from
        the artifact that it manages and to incorporate the data that is sent
        from the variants management tool into this artifact. Beyond the
        exchange format, i.e. the contents of the information that is
        exchanged, also some basic operations are defined here. They define in
        which direction the variability information is intended to
        flow.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Use case for the Variability Exchange Language</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="344" contentwidth="534"
                         fileref="Figures/image1.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>A use case for the <emphasis>Variability Exchange
        Language</emphasis> can be defined as follows. Assume an artifact with
        variation points is given, for instance an artifact created with tool
        A in <xref linkend="_Ref408318739"/>. First the development tool has
        to collect the data defined in the <emphasis>Variability Exchange
        Language, </emphasis>essentially given by the variation points
        contained in the artifact. It passes this data to the variants
        management tool that builds a variability model based on the data. The
        variability model can be used to define a system configuration by
        selecting the desired system features. The corresponding data, i.e.
        the configuration, formatted according to the <emphasis>Variability
        Exchange Language</emphasis>, is passed back to the development tool
        or adaptor that uses this data to create or derive an artifact variant
        that corresponds to the system variant defined in the variants
        management tool.</para>

        <para>Applying this scenario to all development tools and artifacts
        yields a consistent set of development artifacts for any system
        variant automatically. The variation points that correspond to
        customer relevant system features should coincide in all artifacts,
        i.e. they always induce the same variability model in the variants
        management tool. In addition to that there may also be internal
        variation points, for instance implementation variants that do not
        alter the visible properties of the system but are relevant for the
        system construction process. These variation points give rise to a
        staged variability model in which customer features are separated from
        internal features.</para>

        <para>Since the system configuration is built once and for all in the
        variants management tool an identical configuration is passed to all
        development tools and thereby ensures consistency of the variants
        selection. It might only happen that internal features for instance
        are not interpreted by some development tool because it is not
        concerned with internal decisions, such as a requirements document or
        a system test.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="S-TERMINOLOGY">
      <title>Terminology</title>

      <section id="S-KEY-WORDS">
        <title>Key words</title>

        <para>The key words <glossterm>must</glossterm>, <glossterm>must
        not</glossterm>, <glossterm>required</glossterm>,
        <glossterm>shall</glossterm>, <glossterm>shall not</glossterm>,
        <glossterm>should</glossterm>, <glossterm>should not</glossterm>,
        <glossterm>recommended</glossterm>, <glossterm>may</glossterm>, and
        <glossterm>optional</glossterm> are to be interpreted as described in
        <xref linkend="rfc2119"/>. Note that for reasons of style, these words
        are not capitalized in this document.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="S-DEFINITIONS">
        <title>Definitions</title>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>term</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Definition</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>term</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Definition</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section id="S-KEY-CONCEPTS">
        <title>Key concepts</title>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>concept</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Definition</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>concept</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Definition</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>concept</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Definition</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="S-NORMATIVE-REFERENCES">
      <title>Normative References</title>

      <bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed id="docbook"><abbrev>DocBook</abbrev> <citetitle>DocBook
        4.5 </citetitle> <date>17 January 2005. </date> <releaseinfo>OASIS
        Committee Draft 4.5. </releaseinfo> <bibliomisc><ulink
        url="https://www.docbook.org/specs/docbook-4.5-spec.html">https://www.docbook.org/specs/docbook-4.5-spec.html</ulink>.</bibliomisc></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="rfc2119"><abbrev>RFC 2119</abbrev> <citetitle>Key
        words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</citetitle>,
        <date>March 1997. </date> <author>
            <firstname>S.</firstname>

            <surname>Bradner</surname>
          </author>. <releaseinfo>IETF (Internet Engineering Task Force) RFC
        2119, </releaseinfo> <bibliomisc><ulink
        url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt">http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt</ulink>.</bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist>
    </section>

    <section id="S-NON-NORMATIVE-REFERENCES">
      <title>Non-Normative References</title>

      <bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed id="oasis-spec"><abbrev>oasis-spec</abbrev>
        <citetitle>OASIS Specification Publishing in DocBook XML Version
        &version;. </citetitle> <date>&pubdate;. </date> <releaseinfo>OASIS
        Working Draft. </releaseinfo> <bibliomisc><ulink
        url="https://docs.oasis-open.org/templates/DocBook/spec-1.0/oasis-specification-1.0-csprd01.html">https://docs.oasis-open.org/templates/DocBook/spec-&version;/oasis-specification-&version;-&stage;.html</ulink>.</bibliomisc></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="xml-assoc"><abbrev>xml-assoc</abbrev>
        <title>Associating Style Sheets with XML documents Version 1.0.
        </title> <date>29 June 1999. </date> <author>
            <firstname>James</firstname>

            <surname>Clark</surname>
          </author>. <releaseinfo>W3C Recommendation. </releaseinfo>
        <bibliomisc><ulink
        url="http://www.w3.org/1999/06/REC-xml-stylesheet-19990629">http://www.w3.org/1999/06/REC-xml-stylesheet-19990629</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="S-SECTION-TITLE">
    <title>Overview of the Variability Exchange Language</title>

    <para>The core of the <emphasis>Variability Exchange Language</emphasis>
    is given by the definition of variation points and their variations
    &ndash; by the classes VariationPoint and Variation (see <xref
    linkend="_Ref408311811"/>). In the following we immediately use the class
    names from the meta-model presented in Chapter <xref
    linkend="_Toc393199827"/> to discuss the corresponding concepts, such as
    VariationPoint and Variation. This chapter gives a survey on the main
    classes, in particular the ones shown in <xref
    linkend="_Ref408311811"/>.</para>

    <para>A detailed specification of all classes is provided in Chapter <xref
    linkend="_Toc393199827"/>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="_Ref408311811">
      <title>An Overview of the Variability Exchange Language</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentdepth="777" contentwidth="605"
                     fileref="Figures/image2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>A [XMLmind] Exchange Language document starts with a
    VariabilityExchangeModels element, which contains a number of
    VariabilityExchangeModel elements. Each VariabilityExchangeModel
    corresponds to one (or possibly several, but this is implementation
    dependent) artefacts with variable elements.</para>

    <para>A VariabilityExchangeModel in turn contains a number of
    VariationPoints. Thus, a VariabilityExchangeModel describes the variable
    aspects of an artifact, but only those. All non-variable facets of the
    artifact are discarded because they are not necessary for our
    purpose.</para>

    <section id="S-SUB-SECTION-TITLE">
      <title>VariationPoint and Variation</title>

      <para>As shown in <xref linkend="_Ref408311811"/>, we distinguish
      between two different kinds of VariationPoints:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>StructuralVariationPoints are variation points where the
          structure of a model changes during the binding process.
          StructuralVariationPoints define which elements are contained in a
          bound artifact. There are two kinds of structural variation
          points:</para>

          <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
              <para>OptionalStructuralVariationPoint &ndash; variation points
              that can be selected or deselected.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>XorStructuralVariationPoint &ndash; i.e. variation points
              that represent sets of alternatives from which exactly one can
              be selected.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ParameterVariationPoints are variation points which select a
          numerical value for a parameter during the binding process. They do
          not change the structure of an artifact. There are two kinds of
          parameter variation points:</para>

          <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
              <para>CalculatedParameterVariationPoint &ndash; variation points
              where the parameter value is calculated by an expression.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>XorParameterVariationPoint &ndash; variation points where
              the parameter value is selected from a list of values.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Each VariationPoint is [XMLmind] with one or more Variations. The
      Variations enumerate the possible variants for their respective
      VariationPoints. When an artifact is bound, then one of these variations
      (OptionalStructuralVariationPoints also allow zero variations here) is
      selected to be included in the bound artifact, and all others are
      discarded.</para>

      <para>Both Variations and VariationPoints may refer to artifact elements
      (correspondingVariableArtifactElement), for example the Simulink block
      or the line of code which correspond to the VariationPoint respectively
      Variation.</para>

      <para>VariationPoints can further define dependencies on other variation
      points (VariationDependency), for example one variation point may
      require another variation points. This is useful to express technical
      dependencies in artifacts.</para>

      <para>Furthermore, a VariationPoint may contain other VariationPoints to
      establish a hierarchy (VariationPointHierarchy), similarly to subsystem
      blocks in Simulink or hierarchies in software architectures.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="_Ref409084549">
      <title>Variation Point Descriptions versus Variation Point
      Selections</title>

      <para>A VariabilityExchangeModel as defined in <xref
      linkend="_Ref408311811"/> can actually serve two different
      purposes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A <emphasis>variation point description</emphasis> lists all
          variation points and <emphasis>all</emphasis> their variations; that
          is it describes a complete product line.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <emphasis>variation point description</emphasis> also lists
          all variation points, but selects one (or zero for optional
          variation points) Variation for each variation point. The attribute
          selected of Variation is used for that purpose. Any such selection
          must be consistent with the expression or condition attribute of a
          Variation, as well as with dependencies between variation
          points.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Both variation point descriptions and variation point selections
      use the same structure; the attribute type of VariabilityExchangeModel
      determines how a VariabilityExchangeModel should be interpreted.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Binding</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>Variability [XMLmind] Language</emphasis> does not
      make any assumptions on how the binding process for the associated
      artifact works. We do however provide a way to attach Conditions or
      Expressions to Variations:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In a StructuralVariationPoint, a Variation comes with a
          Condition that determines whether the associated artifact element is
          part of a bound artifact.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In a ParameterVariationPoint, the Variation determines a value
          for the associated artifact element. This is done either by
          computing it (CalculatedVariation) or selecting from one of several
          values (ValueVariation).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In a variation point description (see section <xref
      linkend="_Ref409084549"/>) the result of the evaluation of a condition
      or expression in a Variation must be compatible with the attribute
      selected of a Variation. That is, if the attribute selected of a
      Variation has the value <emphasis>true</emphasis>, then its condition
      must also evaluate to <emphasis>true</emphasis>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Common Concepts</title>

      <para>Most classes in the <emphasis>Variability Exchange
      Language</emphasis> are based on the class Identifiable, which provides
      them with a name and a unique identifier. Identifable also provide a way
      to attach application-specific data (SpecialData) to elements in the
      <emphasis>Variability Exchange Language</emphasis>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>API</title>

      <para>In addition to the contents of the exchange format basic
      operations of a Variability Interface are defined in the class
      VariabilityAPI. These operations cover the following operations:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The import and export of VariabilityExchangeModels</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Getting and setting configurations, which are also
          VariabilityExchangeModels</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Getting [XMLmind] on the read or write access (Capability) to
          VariationPoints and VariabilityExchangeModels as
          configurations.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Example</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>#if A</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>/* code active if A is defined */</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>#if B</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>/* code active if A and B is defined */</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>#endif</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>/* code active if A is defined */</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>#else</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>/* code active if A is not defined */</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>#endif</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>To demonstrate the applicability of the Variability Exchange
      Language for the exchange of variability information, we show as an
      example a simple source code section (see <xref
      linkend="_Ref13056146"/>), in which the C-preprocessor (cpp) is employed
      to realize variability, and the extract of that variability defined
      according to Variability Exchange Language (see <xref
      linkend="_Ref13056667"/>). We could have used further artifact types
      like requirements, UML models, tests, etc. but for the sake of
      simplicity and understandability we opted for C-source code using the
      cpp.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>...</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;variability-exchange-model
          type="variationpoint-description" id="model"
          uri="file///c:/example.c"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;xor-structural-variationpoint id="vp1"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;corresponding-variable-artifact-element
          type="src-lines"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;src-lines&gt;1-9&lt;/src-lines&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/corresponding-variable-artifact-element&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;variation id="vp1v1" &gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;condition
          [XMLmind]="single-feature-condition"&gt;A&lt;/condition&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;corresponding-variable-artifact-element
          type="src-lines"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;src-lines&gt;2-6&lt;/src-lines&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/corresponding-variable-artifact-element&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;hierarchy id="vp2h1"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;variationpoint ref="vp2"/&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/hierarchy&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/variation&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;variation id="vp1v2"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;corresponding-variable-artifact-element
          type="src-lines"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;src-lines&gt;8&lt;/src-lines&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/corresponding-variable-artifact-element&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/variation&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/xor-structural-variationpoint&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;optional-structural-variationpoint id="vp2"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;corresponding-variable-artifact-element
          type="src-lines"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;src-lines&gt;3-5&lt;/src-lines&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/corresponding-variable-artifact-element&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;variation id="vp1v1" &gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;condition
          type="single-feature-condition"&gt;B&lt;/condition&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;corresponding-variable-artifact-element
          [XMLmind]="src-lines"&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;src-lines&gt;4&lt;/src-lines&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/corresponding-variable-artifact-element&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/variation&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/optional-structural-variationpoint&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>&lt;/variability-exchange-model&gt;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>... </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>To note, the cpp is a stand-alone tool for text processing, which,
      although initially invented for C, is not limited to a specific language
      and can be used for arbitrary text and source code transformations <link
      linkend="PS">[Fav96],</link> leading e.g. to conditional code
      compilation. The cpp tool works on the basis of directives (a.k.a.
      macros) that control syntactic program transformations. The directives
      supported by the cpp tool can be divided into four classes: file
      inclusion, macro definition, macro substitution, and conditional
      inclusion.</para>

      <para>In our example, we only use the macros <emphasis>A</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>B</emphasis> and conditional inclusion mechanisms. The source
      code comments in <xref linkend="_Ref13056146"/> explain how the cpp will
      transform the code depending on the definition of the macros. From an
      abstract point of view, the code contains two variation points and three
      variations, which is reflected according to the Variability Exchange
      Language in the exchange format definition in <xref
      linkend="_Ref13056667"/>. The first variation point spans the source
      lines 1-9 and contains two alternative variations. The variation point's
      corresponding elements of the artifact &ndash; in this case exactly the
      source lines &ndash; are represented in the exchange format as well.
      Regarding the variations, the first one (lines 2-6) will be selected if
      macro A is defined. Otherwise the second variation (line 8) gets
      selected. Assuming that the macro names are identically with features or
      at least there exists a mapping from a feature to a macro name, then the
      <emphasis>condition</emphasis> in the eighth line in <xref
      linkend="_Ref13056667"/> is the equivalent to the first source code
      line.</para>

      <para>The [XMLmind] variation point (lines 3-5) is nested within the
      first variation of the first variation point, constituting a variation
      point hierarchy. Within the corresponding exchange format, the variation
      points are not nested but the nesting information is covered by the
      definition in the lines 15-17 in <xref linkend="_Ref13056667"/>. There,
      the nested variation point is referenced by its <emphasis>id</emphasis>,
      resulting in a tree-like structure at the end.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Toc393199827">
    <title>Variability Exchange Language Class Reference</title>

    <para>The last section contains the conformance clauses/statements.</para>
  </section>

  <appendix id="A-AN-ANNEX">
    <title>An Annex</title>

    <para>Appendices are distinguished from sections.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="A-A-NORMATIVE-ANNEX" role="normative">
    <title>A Normative Annex</title>

    <para>An annex or section with <literal>role="normative"</literal>.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="A-A-NON-NORMATIVE-ANNEX" role="non-normative">
    <title>A Non-normative Annex</title>

    <para>An annex or section with
    <literal>role="non-normative"</literal>.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="A-AN-INFORMATIVE-ANNEX" role="informative">
    <title>An Informative Annex</title>

    <para>An annex or section with
    <literal>role="informative"</literal>.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="A-AN-ISO-NORMATIVE-ANNEX" role="iso-normative">
    <title>An ISO-normative Annex</title>

    <para>An annex or section with
    <literal>role="iso-normative"</literal>.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="A-AN-ISO-INFORMATIVE-ANNEX" role="iso-informative">
    <title>An ISO-informative Annex</title>

    <para>An annex or section with
    <literal>role="iso-informative"</literal>.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="A-ACKNOWLEDGMENTS" role="non-normative">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>

    <para>In a typical OASIS work product one might wish to list committee
    participants in a non-normative annex (markup shown above in the normative
    annex example) using wording along the line of &ldquo;The following
    individuals have participated in the creation of this specification and
    are gratefully acknowledged:&rdquor;</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Mary Baker, Associate Member</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Jane Doe, Example Corporation Member</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>John Able, Other Example Corporation Member</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Note that the itemized list uses
    <literal>spacing="compact"</literal> to remove the space between list
    items in the printed result, not the HTML result.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix id="A-REVISION-HISTORY">
    <title>Revision History</title>

    <para>Typically the revision history is removed from a finalized
    specification or note.</para>

    <para><revhistory>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>X.Y</revnumber>

          <date>DD Mmmmmm YYYY</date>

          <authorinitials>abc</authorinitials>

          <revremark>Details of the revision</revremark>
        </revision>

        <revision>
          <revnumber>X.Y</revnumber>

          <date>DD Mmmmmm YYYY</date>

          <authorinitials>abc</authorinitials>

          <revremark>Details of the revision</revremark>
        </revision>
      </revhistory></para>
  </appendix>
</article>
